Finding Aid for Amos R. Green Papers 1932-1967
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Amos R. Green Papers 1932-1967
Green, Amos R., 1887-1968.
Amateur archeologist and historian from Niles (Berrien County), Michigan. Biographical and personal material; correspondence; publications; talks, radio interviews and other public presentations; archeological site notes and reports; research sources and notes; maps; photographs; and files relating to his activities with the southwest chapter, Michigan Archeological Society; contain materials relating to his interest in the archaeology, Indian anthropology, and history of the area around Berrien and Cass Counties; also papers documenting his relationship with professionals in various disciplines at the University of Michigan Museums and elsewhere.
85189 Ac Aa 2
2.2 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Donald P. Hays and W.N. Beverly, Jr. on behalf of the Michigan Archeological Society (donor no. 6949 ), June 20, 1983.
The collection is open for research.
Amos Green was by trade a farmer. He also raised and sold flowers for a time and earned money by selling agricultural supplies for the Dekalb Agricultural Association, Inc. in and around Berrien County, Michigan. But Green's passion in life was archaeology and local history. To read his correspondence one would think he was a professional archeologist, for farming receives only an occasional and passing reference; he remained, however, highly conscious that he was an amateur. Though with only a high school degree, he immersed himself in the literature of archaeology, paleontology, geology, and anthropology. He threw himself, too, into the practice of archaeology, excavating burial mounds and surveying construction sites. Green was also a leader in the reconstitution and growth of the Michigan Archeological Society (MAS), an organization that brought amateur and professional together. Green early earned the respect of the professionals with whom he worked; he published papers in prestigious journals and he corresponded regularly and familiarly with the professors at the University of Michigan museums of paleontology, archaeology, and anthropology. In addition, Green earned the esteem of his community, for much of his energy went into outreach programs to encourage farmers and other citizens to be more aware of and take an active interest in the history and prehistory of Berrien County.
Green began his archeological work in 1913 when, with Harvey Franz, he excavated the Franz Green Mound in Porter County, Indiana. Service in World War I and the care of his farm and ailing mother apparently kept his other activities to a minimum until the 1940s, when he returned to the field for several excavations.
In 1946 the Michigan Academy for Sciences, Letters, and the Arts published one of his papers, "The Bevel in Steel and Stone Tools," which he had presented at an earlier Academy meeting. Among his more important "professional" activities in the following years were the presentation of papers at the 1952 meeting of the Central States Anthropological Society and at the 1956 meeting of the American Archeological Society, the supervision of the excavation of the Horseshoe Ditch at Sumnerville in 1954 and an archeological survey of a portion of the Muskegon Pipeline in 1957, the preparation of an educational filmstrip to be distributed through MAS in 1958. After helping to revive the MAS in 1950, Green served for eight years as president of the Southwest Chapter, and for 17 years on the executive board of MAS central. In Berrien County, he was the unofficial contact person for citizens who made archeological finds (the most important of which was the "Prillwitz" Mammoth in 1962), wrote newspaper articles and gave talks on local archaeology and history, and successfully promoted the marking of historic sites. For example, during the 1960s he created a series of short radio programs on the early history of Ft. St. Joseph, gave radio interviews on the early culture of Michigan's native Americans, and successfully promoted the marking of the site of a French Jesuit mission in Berrien Springs.
Green never married. He remained active until he was mortally injured in a car accident in May of 1968. He died on July 18, 1968, at the age of 81.
The collection touches on most aspects of Green's life from 1940 to 1967. Material on his business activities is, however, minimal. It is his archeological and historical work that the collection documents most thoroughly. Green's correspondence is full of reports, inquiries, and discussions about the theoretical and practical facets of archaeology, focusing largely upon fossil and artifact finds in southwestern Michigan; the letters also illuminate the occasionally trying relationship between professionals and amateurs in the field. The practical aspect of archaeology is documented, too, in an incomplete assortment of Green's site notes. Green's historical research interests are well represented in his correspondence, as well as in some interesting source material and notes on Ft. St. Joseph and on Jesuit missions in Berrien County. Most of Green's writings on both archaeology and history--in the guise of formal papers and informal presentations--are included. A large number of newspaper clippings provide an overview of the activities and achievements of both Green and the Southwest Chapter of MAS. Chapter activities are also documented in its newsletter, its annual reports, and its miscellaneous mailings.
The collection contains virtually nothing on Green's life to 1932, thus omitting his work on the Franz Green Mound. From 1932 through 1939 only scattered portions of correspondence exist. Documentation is substantial, though still not complete, for the years 1940 through 1967; in places letters are obviously missing from the correspondence file, no draft exists of Green's 1961 paper, "An Adena-type Gorget in Michigan," and neither his filmstrip nor a final draft of the narrative for it is extant. Neither Green's large artifact collection nor his library is represented. The collection contains virtually nothing about his farming activities or his family.
The Amos Green Papers have been arranged into nine series: Biographical and Personal, Correspondence, Publications and Presentations, Archeological Fieldwork: Site Notes and Reports, Research, Maps, MAS Southwest Chapter, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Anthropology.; Archaeology.; Berrien County (Mich.); Berrien Springs (Mich.); Cass County (Mich.); Green, Amos R., 1887-1968.; Indians of North America--Michigan.; Michigan Archaeological Society.; Michigan--History.; Niles (Mich.); University of Michigan. University Museum.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Archaeology.; Fossils.; Indian weapons--North America.; Mills--Michigan--Summerville.; Sumnerville (Mich.)--Mills.
Contributors:
Fitting, James Edward.; Greenman, Emerson Frank, 1895-1973.; Hibbard, James.; Witthoft, John.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical and personal
  The autobiographical file includes statements from 1956 and 1962, the former being the most exemplary of how seriously Green took his archeological work. The clippings cover Green's archeological field work, his public talks, his MAS activities, and his efforts at marking historical sites. Most of the clippings are dated. The memorabilia includes programs of conferences Green attended and publications that refer to his work. Two folders contain scattered information on his stints as florist and as farm products salesman.
  - Autobiographical Statements (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Archeological Fieldwork (Box 1)
    - Talks and Tours, MAS (Box 1)
    - Talks and Tours, Public (Box 1)
    - Michigan History Work (Box 1)
    - Memorabilia (Box 1)
  - Shanghai Gardens circa 1947-1950 (Box 1)
  - Dekalb Dealership circa 1948-1952 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1897, 1932-1967
  Green's correspondence file includes copies of most of his outgoing letters, as well as his incoming mail. It contains virtually no personal information, but documents Green's fieldwork, his writing and publishing, his constant search for primary sources for Berrien County history, and, to a lesser extent, his MAS activities. The correspondence details, too, his long relationship with several members of the archeological profession: John Witthoft of the Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission and the American Archeological Society; E. F. Greenman of the University of Michigan Museum of Archaeology and editor of the Michigan Archeologist (MAS); James Fitting of the University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology and successor to Greenman as editor of the Michigan Archeologist; and James Hibbard of the University of Michigan Museum of Paleontology. Perhaps the most interesting aspect of the correspondence is the light it sheds on the relationship between amateurs and professionals in archaeology. For all of his credentials, Green remained always conscious of being "a 'Sunday afternoon archeologist, '" and he remained either diffident or defensive in his relations with all Ph.D.s, no matter how long he had known them. On the other hand, his position was that of intermediary between the two worlds, and the professionals seemed to value him precisely because he served as their bridge to the public and vice versa.
  - 1897, 1904 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - 1932-1936 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - 1938 (Box 1)
  - 1940-1945 (Box 1)
  - 1946-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1940s (Box 1)
  - 1950-1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1963 (Box 1)
  - 1964-1967 (Box 1)
  - Undated (Box 1)
- Publications and Presentations
  Publications and Presentations Includes typescripts of Green's formal papers as well as an occasional early draft. Most of these works were later published; all were intended for publication. His paper on the Prillwitz Mammoth apparently engendered so much controversy that he withdrew it voluntarily from publication in the Michigan Archeologist (a "history of this paper" is also included). The reports to the Southwest Chapter of the MAS are less formal and much briefer; some are fragmentary. His informal public presentations included short educational talks, radio interviews, narrated slide presentations, and historic tours, all of which are represented here.
  - Formal Papers and Articles 1946-1965
    - 1946 "The Bevel in Stone and Steel Tools and the Benefits to Man" (Box 1)
    - 1952 "A Fluted Point and Archaic Relationships" (Box 1)
    - 1954 "The Horseshoe Ditch at the Sumnerville Mound Group" (Box 1)
    - 1956 "A New Industry Found in Southwestern Michigan" (Box 1)
    - 1958 "The Archeological Survey of the Muskegon Pipeline" (Box 1)
    - 1958 "Find Indian Burial Dated 2350 Years" (Box 1)
    - 1961 "Once a Mission at Berrien Springs" (Box 1)
    - 1964 "A Red Ochre Cache in Berrien County, Michigan" (Box 1)
    - 1964 "A Cache of Thirty-four Turkey-Tail Artifacts Found in Berrien County, Michigan" (Box 1)
    - 1965 "Prillwitz Mammoth Killed in a Paleo-Indian Hunt 8260 Years Ago" (Box 1)
    - Prints of Published Works (Box 1)
  - Reports to MAS, Southwest Chapter
    - Talks
      - "Banner Stones" (Box 1)
      - "The Dean Bowl Area Rich in Geological, Paleontology [sic], and Archeological History" (Box 1)
      - "The Flaking of Stone Tools" (Box 1)
      - "A Late Woodland Indian Oven" (Box 1)
      - "Two Surface Points Found that Might Be Saws" (Box 1)
  - Slide Narratives
    - "The Boone Grove Mound Group and the Franz Green Mound," March 10, 1957 (Box 1)
    - "Prehistory Indians" (Box 1)
  - Informal Public Presentations
    - Talks
      - "Michigan's Foundations" (Box 1)
      - "Packages of Furs Received [at] Trading Posts at French Forts in 1757" (Box 1)
      - "The Sumnerville Indian Mounds" (Box 1)
      - "What the Whiteman [sic] Received from the Indian" (Box 1)
      - "When the Whiteman [sic] Came to America" (Box 1)
    - Radio Interviews
      - "When the First Indians Came to Michigan," October 26, 1958 (Box 1)
      - [Prehistoric Indian Cultures in Michigan] November 21, 1961 (Box 1)
      - [Prillwitz Mammoth] 1962 (Box 1)
      - "Buffalo in Southwestern Michigan," circa 1962 (Box 1)
    - Others
      - "Illustrated Tour of Niles-Bertrand Area," Slide Narration, Berrien Springs PTA (Box 1)
      - [Tour of Ft. St. Joseph and Related Indian Sites] (Box 1)
      - [Scientists Depend on Eyes of Amateurs,] (Box 1)
        Incomplete Rough Draft
- Archeological Fieldwork: Site Notes And Reports
  The series Archeological Fieldwork: Site Notes And Reports is composed of Green's onsite notes and some brief typed reports. (Other reports are found in the correspondence and presentations series.) The notes are usually in pencil and rather fragmentary or cryptic, but some include maps, sketches, and diagrams. The dates for much of the work are unknown, and many of the sites are not referred to distinctly in Green's correspondence--they may represent work done before 1940, perhaps as early as the 1910s.
  - Ament Site, School Section Lake (Box 1)
  - Bloomer Pits 1955 (Box 1)
  - Bowman Mud Lake, Site 93 (Box 1)
  - Dean Bowl circa 1949 (Box 1)
  - Filgurites In Geneva Township (Box 1)
  - "Folsom Notes Locally" (Box 1)
  - Grant Site on Brandywine Creek March 1947 (Box 1)
  - Green's Hi-Lo Site circa 1963 (Box 1)
  - Haskell Site 1952 (Box 1)
  - Horseshoe Ditch at Sumnerville Mound Group 1954 (Box 1)
  - Kimmel Site 1958 (Box 1)
  - Murphey Mound (Box 1)
  - Muskegon Pipeline 1958 (Box 1)
  - Prillwitz Mammoth 1962 (Box 1)
  - Putnam and Babcock Graves (Box 1)
  - Storage Pits in Cass County 1955 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Research
  The sources subseries within the Research series represents a sampling of the secondary sources (and some primary sources) which Green used in the preparation of his papers or simply to increase his overall knowledge of subjects he was interested in. Much of the material is in the form of mimeos or stencils, and hence not readily available elsewhere. The notes subseries represents subjects for which Green compiled fairly extensive (and legible) handwritten notes, and includes a small notecard file. The subjects represented are all also found in either his correspondence or writings.
  - Sources
    - Archaeology
      - Mimeos and Stencils (Box 1)
      - Printed (Box 1)
    - Michigan History
      - General (Box 1)
      - Berrien County Centennial (Box 1)
      - Native Americans (Box 1)
      - Style Manuals (Box 1)
  - Notes
    - Basswood Bark as Thread (Box 2)
    - Buffalo Hunt by Indians (Box 2)
    - Ft. St. Joseph (Box 2)
    - Giant Beaver (Box 2)
    - Pipestone Merchants (Box 2)
    - Tools in Early Indian Culture (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Notecard File and Notebooks (Box 2)
- Maps
  Maps. The filmstrip illustrations depict several sites at which Green excavated, and generally provide a record of archeological activity in Southwestern Michigan and northern Indiana. Of the other maps, the most interesting are those of early Michigan towns and townships. Several of these maps are oversized, and are stored separately from the bulk of the collection. The filmstrip illustrations and some of the other maps are hand drawn, whether by Green or someone else is unclear.
  - For Filmstrip Illustrations (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Photostat of Twp. No. 8 South, Range No. 17 West, Michigan (Box 2)
    - Photostat of Land Ownership Northeast of Eau Claire (Box 2)
    - Michigan (Box 2)
    - Historic Indian Paths of Pennsylvania (Box 2)
    - St. Joseph County Roadmap (annotated) (Box 2)
    - Unlabeled Mound Group, Cass County (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Oversized folder; stored separately)
    - St. Joseph River "Meander," Schematic (Box 2)
    - Photostat Survey Plat of Newberryport, Michigan August 16, 1910 (Box 2)
    - Pipestone Twp. Cemetery Addition 1948 (Box 2)
    - Pipestone Twp. Cemetery February 1955 (Box 2)
    - Unlabeled Grid (Cass County?) (Box 2)
- Michigan Archaeological Society, Southwest Chapter
  The Michigan Archaeological Society, Southwest Chapter series is most important as documentation of the activities of amateur archeologists in Michigan. The extent and quality of chapter work is illustrated most clearly in the chapter newsletters, the mailings announcing chapter events and activities, and the clippings file. The series is much less the records of Green as president of the chapter than of Green as member of the chapter.
  - Annual Reports 1951-1956 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with MAS Central (Box 2)
  - Report of MAS Filmstrip Committee 1957-1958 (Box 2)
  - Reports on Chapter Activities (Box 2)
  - Members, Officers, Committees 1951-1952, 1957-1958 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter 1953-1964, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Mimeo and Stencil Publications (Box 2)
  - Announcements of Events and Activities (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings about Activities (Box 2)
  - List of Local Fossil and Artifact Collections to Be Surveyed (Box 2)
  - Artifact Collection Survey Summaries circa 1954-1955 (Box 2)
  - "Archeological Survey of Michigan" (Forms for Berrien and Pipestone Twps.) (Box 2)
- Photographs
  Most of the images in the photographs series depict excavation work, excavation sites, fossils, or artifacts. The precision of their dating and labeling varies tremendously. There are no personal photos in the collection, but photos of Green himself can be found in the biographical clippings file.
  - Archaeological sites and excavations, unidentified (Box 3)
  - Artifacts: Beveled Points paper 1946 New Industry Paper, 1956 Sandia Points and others including the Hi-Lo site (Box 3)
  - Excavations, Floyd Haskins farm 1956 (Box 3)
    includes skeletons and accompanying jewelry
  - Mastodon fossils (including Berndt mastodon teeth) and McNeill site, Berrien County [photos: L.B. Killum,1950] (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Muskegon Pipeline article: illustrations January 1958 (Box 3)
  - Prillwitz Mammoth materials 1962, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Sumnerville Mill 1884 and Sumnerville Mound Group, aerial photograph of Horseshoe Ditch 1954